Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting New Haven, Connecticut
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Interviews, Accession 2008-A-001
  - O'Connell, Craig, 2003 July 2; computer file (WAV)
    Craig O'Connell was a teacher in several New Haven elementary schools and the founder of Teachers for a Progressive Union. Born in New Haven in 1947, O'Connell grew up in a working-class family in Newhallville. He attended Catholic School, graduated from Fairfield University, and became a fourth grade teacher in Newhallville in 1969. In the 1970s, he worked for the Martin Luther King School, a charter program that tried to foster community involvement in the schools. Most of O'Connell's interview covers his experience in the teacher's union. He first went on strike in 1970 and recalls that few other elementary school teachers joined him on the picket line. After the thirteen-day strike, however, O'Connell began to organize fellow teachers at his school. He also formed the group Teachers for a Progressive Union, a radical organization that addressed issues of racism, civil rights, gender inequities, class size, and working conditions. This group, O'Connell notes, was at odds with other union leaders and the Board of Education, which focused on traditional issues such as salaries and benefits. O'Connell also talks about the teachers strikes in 1973 and 1975, how hard-line stances from the Board of Education helped nurture public support for teachers, and how the culture of teaching has changed since the 1970s.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Oliva, Linda, 2004 February 24; computer file (WAV)
  - Patton, Curtis, 2005 April 21; computer file (WAV)
    Born in Birmingham in 1935, Curtis Patton began to fight for civil rights from an early age, a commitment he carried with him to Yale in the 1970s. In high school, Patton joined the youth division of the NAACP. He remembers hearing a 1951 speech by Mordecai Johnson, the president of Howard University, which predicted the coming Civil Rights movement. After graduating high school, Patton attended Fisk University which he describes as a center of civil rights activism. At Fisk, Patton's professors encouraged disobedience as a way to protest segregation. He recounts occasions when he broke racial barriers in movie theaters and on trains. He also remembers the two times he encountered Martin Luther King, Jr., in 1955 Montgomery and at Fisk the following year. Patton attended the University of Michigan during the 1960s and discusses watching events unfold in Alabama from afar. In 1970, he became an assistant professor at Yale. A large portion of the interview focuses on Patton's hero, Edward Bouchet, an African American servant to a white Yale student who earned a Ph.D. in physics from Yale in the 1870s. Patton concludes with a discussion of the Black Power Movement and how it differed from the Civil Rights Movement.
    Interviewer: Koh, Emily, and Greer, Bryan
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Pearce, Herb, 2005 August 3; computer file (WAV)
    Herb Pearce grew up in New Haven, graduated from Commercial (later Wilbur Cross) High School in 1935, and went to work for the A. C. Gilbert Company in Fair Haven for the next twenty-one years. Pearce knew the Gilbert family because he delivered newspapers to their home and it was this personal relationship that helped him secure a full-time job during the Great Depression. Pearce discusses the various jobs that he performed at the toy factory. He began building models for department store displays, then became an inspector, a manager, and, after World War II, represented the company's sales department in Ohio and Michigan. He remembers A. C. Gilbert as a family-oriented man who paid attention to workers' grievances and interests. These traits, Pearce believed, kept workers happy and prevented unions from getting a foothold in the factory. Pearce also touches on the factory's shift to wartime production from 1941 to 1945, the large number of female workers in the factory, and what the average work day looked like. The interview concludes with a discussion of his decision to leave the factory in 1957 to start his own business, A. C. Gilbert's death in 1961, and the sale of the company the following year.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Piascik, Ray, 2007 April 12; computer file (WAV)
    Ray Piascik works for the U.S. Postal Service. He has lived in New Haven his whole life, and currently works for the Yale branch of the USPS on Elm Street. He is a life-long fan of the rock band the Doors. Piascik says that he attended roughly ten doors concerts during the band's existence. In this interview, Piascik describes the events at a Doors concert in New Haven, during which Jim Morrison -- the Doors' lead singer -- was arrested. The arrest sparked a small riot in the arena. Piascik also describes his other musical interests, and meeting the Rolling Stones at the airport.
    Interviewer: Bucknoff, Zach
    Length (min): 23
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Pierce, Patricia, 2005 December 2; computer file (WAV)
    In 1970, recently separated and the mother of four small children, Patricia Pierce chose to attend the May Day demonstrations on the New Haven Green. The event marked a turning point in her political activism and awareness. Pierce grew up in an upper-middle class family and attended Vassar. She came to New Haven in 1964 because her then husband, attorney Cheever Tyler, got a job at the Wiggin and Dana law firm. Although the couple had separated by the spring of 1970, Tyler instructed Pierce to take their four children to Branford to avoid potential violence on May 1. She left her children with a friend and came back to New Haven to observe the activity for an hour or so. Pierce reflects on the events of the day and the political consciousness that she began to develop in their aftermath. She talks about becoming an activist in the 1970s, the women's movement, her decision to get a Ph.D., and her later community involvement with Planned Parenthood and the Amistad Academy charter school. Pierce, the Dean of the Yale School of Management at the time of the interview, also discusses the political apathy that she perceives among undergraduates today.
    Interviewer: Hung, Annie
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Pisani, Lawrence, 2005 March 18; computer file (WAV)
    Lawrence Pisani graduated from Yale College in 1942 and received his Ph.D. in 1951. He talks about his father, an Italian immigrant who covered Connecticut for New York City's Italian daily newspaper and published his own weekly paper for the New Haven Italian community. Pisani discusses the role of these and other local Italian papers in nurturing Italian community. The papers offered information to help immigrants assimilate and become naturalized U.S. citizens. Yet at the same time they served as tools to preserve pride in Italian regional and national heritage and to keep readers abreast of social and cultural events in the Italian communities around New Haven. Pisani discusses the way that members of the Italian community and newspapers reacted to Mussolini. While he believes that most denounced him after he allied with Hitler, he notes that in the 1920s many Italians (and Americans) believed Mussolini might bring progress to Italy. Although he touches on Mussolini and fascism here, Pisani says that the main focus of the newspapers was in social and cultural cohesion rather than political reporting.
    Length (min): 30
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Pullen, Carl, 2004 October 15; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Yellesetty, Leela
    Length (min): 27
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Pullen, Carl, 2006 November 30; computer file (WAV)
    Carl Pullen grew up in Bridgeport but moved to New Haven after graduating high school to work for the police department. He talks about his experiences as an African American police officer in the city during the Civil Rights movement. Pullen and other minority police officers faced discrimination in the police force. Pullen claims that the examinations for promotion were biased and that minority officers received the worst assignments in the roughest areas of the city, such as his assignment to Dixwell Avenue. In the 1970s, Pullen became involved with the Silver Shield organization, a society within the Police Department that became a force for civil rights and anti-discrimination. Pullen and several other officers filed and won a lawsuit that alleged discrimination. Afterwards, New Haven appointed its first African American Chief of Police and dismantled barriers to promotion for African Americans, Latinos, Asians, and women. Pullen also recounts his experiences with the May Day Strikes and the Black Panthers. After retiring, Pullen earned a Master's degree in History, worked for the Hamden School System, and then joined Yale University's security department. He briefly recounts his experiences at Yale and with students there.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Pullen, Carl, 2007 February 15; computer file (WAV)
    Carl Pullen joined the New Haven Police Department in 1962 after serving in the Marine Corps and worked as a patrolman and detective for thirteen years. This interview focuses on his experiences on the police force in the 1960s. Pullen remembers the era as a period of great social unrest. He recalls working in the Hill section as a plainclothes officer during the May Day Demonstrations. He tells the story of arresting Doors' lead singer Jim Morrison at a 1967 concert. Although the media and many fans claimed that the police mistreated Morrison, Pullen discounts their allegations. He also talks about the protests of the 1960s. Pullen admits that he agreed with the sentiments of some protesters but not necessarily their radicalism. He also felt the professional imperative to remain a neutral party. Pullen talks further about his experience as an African American police officer, the discrimination that he and other minorities faced, and the successful lawsuit that he and other officers filed that won better assignments, promotions, and fairer hiring for women and ethnic minorities.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Rae, Douglas, 2006 February 23; computer file (WAV)
    Douglas Rae is a Professor of Political Science at Yale University. He talks about his involvement with the mayoral candidacy of John Daniels. After Daniels' victory, Rae became his Chief Administrator. The central political strategy going into the election, and the central initiative coming out, was a program of community policing to help lower crime in New Haven without "equipping white cops with nightsticks to beat up on black people." Rae describes the trouble with the New Haven police department in attempting to institute a community policing program, and the steps taken by Mayor Daniels to restructure the NHPD after his election. The Daniels administration attempted to attract more women and minorities, and, in an effort to increase trust between the community and the police force, the mayor recruited officers born and raised in the inner-city neighborhoods in which they worked. The key to effective policing, Rae suggests, is an engaged populace and a police force that approaches the community with civility, rather than treating it as a adversary to be conquered. Rae is optimistic about the city's future, and pleased to see how far it has come.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Ragozzino, Thomas, 2004 October 27; computer file (WAV)
    Tom Ragozzino was a history teacher and principal in the New Haven public school system from 1963 until he retried in 1998. His interview focuses on racial tensions at Lee High School, where he was a history teacher, on race riots at Lee and other area high schools, and on the effects of the riots on the school system in the 1970s. Ragozzino discusses the December 1967 race riot at Hillhouse High School, the February 1967 eruption at Lee High School, and several other racially motivated disturbances at other schools. He suggests that the climate of the late 1960s, defined by national race riots, the Civil Rights Movement, drugs, violence, and changing demographics within the schools, infiltrated New Haven's school populations and that administrators. Ragozzino believes the older generation of teachers and guidance counselors had no idea how to react to growing racial issues. He also blames outside agitation for increasing tensions in the schools and the media for overblowing minor events. He then criticizes the 1970s curricular and institutional reforms that occurred in response to the riots, which he believes led to a decline in standards that ultimately hurt students more than it helped them. Ragozzino also touches on issues of white flight, changes in the racial makeup of students, teachers, and the administration, and high turnover in the school system. He also criticizes the charges that many teachers were racist and blames vocal minorities for making such accusations.
    Interviewer: Levine, Katherine
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Ramos, Rafael, 2007 March 30; computer file (WAV)
    Rafael Ramos is the producer for the Bregamos Theater in Fair Haven. Bregamos is a community theater whose mission is to bridge cultures, encourage intergenerational projects, and introduce Fair Haven residents to all aspects of the theater. Bregamos, Ramos explains, roughly translates to "We'll work it out." The theater aims to build community through collaboration and to make theater accessible to individuals who have had little experience with it. The theater offers after-school workshops to introduce young people to acting and production. It encourages alternative theater, such as hip hop musicals. Ramos also discusses the theater's relationship to the larger arts community in New Haven.
    Interviewer: Snell, Sabrina
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Richardson, James, 2003 November 7; computer file (WAV)
    James Richardson grew up in Brooklyn, New York and later moved to New Haven, where he is now a priest, local activist, and community organizer. Richardson describes his growing interest in the church, starting from his membership in religious communities in Belgium and France and, later, Canada, Baltimore, and Chicago. He describes his membership as ethnically and economically diverse, talking about the staff's broad-based efforts to appeal to the entire congregation. He discusses the challenges of creating a sense of religious community amidst cultural and economic differences. He also talks about the church as a site of cross-cultural worship and communication, despite these differences. He describes the importance of church members uniting to help each other and to help other local churches and community service organizations interested in helping people improve their housing situations. He details his church's recent public service projects in education, employment, housing, health care, community service, and mentorship, all to encourage a sense of community in New Haven neighborhoods.
    Interviewer: Manville, Laura
    Length (min): 74
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Robinson, Yakeita, May, 2006; computer file (WAV)
    Yakeita Robinson was born in Bridgeport, CT, and moved to New Haven after 8th grade. In 2001, during her sophomore year at Hillhouse High School, a LEAP (Leadership, Education, and Athletics in Partnership) recruiter visited her school, prompting Robinson to apply for a job as a counselor. She has worked with LEAP since that time, rising to the rank of Site Coordinator. Robinson has been stationed in the Church Street South area since she began. Robinson discusses her work with the Church Street South community and her administrative responsibilities at LEAP, as well as the ethnic, racial, and geographic make-up of children in the program. Robinson stresses that LEAP's primary importance is providing participants with opportunities otherwise unavailable in their communities, including computer classes, karate and dance classes, public speaking courses, and swimming pool access. Along with her work with LEAP, Robinson has a degree in cosmetology and hopes to own a business some day.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Roldan, Zulma, 2007 February 27; computer file (WAV)
    Zulma Roldan moved to the Chatham Square area of Fair Haven in 1984 and has lived there ever since. She discusses the neighborhood and its community. Roldan's parents came to the United States from Puerto Rico and also live in the neighborhood with her. She teaches at the nearby Columbus School. Roldan appreciates the diversity of the neighborhood and the mixture of ethnic backgrounds represented there. She celebrates the community involvement of her neighbors and believes that the city of New Haven and Chatham Square residents have cooperated to make it a good place to live and work. She also talks about her parents' experiences as Puerto Rican immigrants in New Haven.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Rosen, David, 2005 November 21; computer file (WAV)
    David Rosen, who grew up in New York City, describes his experiences practicing law in 1969 at New Haven Legal Assistance, a legal aid office. He shares anecdotes about his interest in civil rights cases. He describes the difficulty of ensuring a fair trial amidst historical judicial racism against black defendants. He discusses his role as a legal assistant on behalf of Black Panther Bobby Seale in the internationally known 1970 dual indictment of Seale and Panther Ericka Huggins for the 1969 murder of fellow Panther Alex Rackley, who was suspected of being an FBI informant. Rosen describes how the mounting local, national, and international racial tensions surrounding the case intensified and complicated legal efforts to withhold confidential trial details from the public. Rosen specifically mentions evidence collection and jury selection as two areas in which he and other Civil Rights lawyers focused. He describes these areas as influencing the pursuit of justice, regardless of the circumstances surrounding the black defendants. He shares what he believes were the case's strengths and weaknesses and evaluates the roles of the counsel, judiciary, and public in both the case's proceedings and the defendants' eventual acquittal. He mentions several key individuals, including distinguished law professor Tom Emerson, Charles Garry, who was Seale's defense lawyer, Katie Rohrback, who was Huggins's defense lawyer, plaintiff and key state witness George Sams, and then-Yale President Kingman Brewster.
    Interviewer: Garcia, Curtis
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Rosenberg, Helene, 2005 October 31; computer file (WAV)
    Helene Rosenberg came to New Haven after World War II. She discusses her experiences as a Polish survivor of the Holocaust and her involvement in New Haven's Holocaust memorial projects. Rosenberg recalls several personal stories about being a Jew in the Warsaw ghetto during World War II, her brushes with the Gestapo, and her eventual capture. A nurse, Rosenberg was forced to work in German hospitals during the war. She also discusses her struggles as an immigrant in New Haven who spoke little English and her efforts to raise her children in the Jewish community. In the 1970s, her husband, the President of the Jewish Federation of New Haven, was one of the driving forces behind the Edgewood Park Holocaust Memorial that was constructed in 1977. Rosenberg recalls his efforts and those of Mayor Frank Logue to create the first Holocaust memorial in the United States. She also talks about the Holocaust survivor film project and the efforts to create a video archive of survivors' stories.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Rosetti, Marilyn, 2004 November 19; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Barrett, Marsha
    Length (min): 76
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Royster, Constance, 2005 May 3; computer file (WAV)
    Constance Royster was born in New Haven, but moved to Bethany, CT while she was in ninth grade. After spending a year at Wheaton College in Massachusetts, Royster transferred to Yale as part of Yale College's first co-ed class. She discusses her experiences at Yale and the difficulties of being a "pioneer." Royster discusses her impressions of the Bobby Seale/Erika Huggins Black Panther trials in 1970, focusing specifically on the manner in which the experience bonded together formerly disparate segments of the Yale and New Haven communities. Erika Huggins, coincidentally, is a distant cousin of Royster's. She also speaks to the nature of racial and gender relations on Yale's campus in the early 1970s. After graduation from Yale, Royster attended law school and became an attorney in New York City. Royster discusses changes she's seen in the New Haven area since her childhood years, including the destruction of important residential and community centers such as the Elm Haven projects. She sees, however, positive changes on the horizion, epitomized by the increasing cleanliness, safety, and vitality of New Haven's downtown.
    Interviewer: Matthews, Emily and Sufrin, Hannah
    Length (min): 51
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Royster, Eunice Baker, 2005 April 26; computer file (WAV)
    Eunice Baker, born in New Haven, recalls the multicultural area of her neighborhood since 1920, sharing anecdotes of her family members and neighborhood friends. She mentions her parents' decision to come to America from the Caribbean island of Saint Kitts and Nevis, following the earlier immigration of her extended family members. She describes the ties and expansion of her U.S. extended family network as they all settled in the New Haven area. She shares anecdotes of playing with her childhood neighbors, many of whose families spoke no English. She discusses her later interest and involvement in social work, starting as an adolescent. She talks about family, friends, education, and church in her community, values that she believes created the sense of a common immigrant experience among culturally and economically diverse individuals and families. She discusses the effect of conflict on her family and community, particularly war and economic instability. She fondly recalls the recreation, music, and media that were popular during her childhood and adult life. She uses examples from her own life and those of various Civil Rights leaders to stress the importance of youth education then and today.
    Interviewer: Jeon, Tinn and Brenner, Nicole
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Saenz, David, 2007 March 6; computer file (WAV)
    David Saenz moved to the Chatham Street neighborhood in Fair Haven five years ago. He discusses some anecdotes from his earlier life, including his rescue of two stray cats. Saenz is mostly content with his neighborhood, but describes a running feud with a neighbor who raises fighting pit bulls next door. The pit bulls, Saenz says, have attacked a number of people and killed one of his cats, but the police refuse to take action. Saenz has harsh words for the police in his neighborhood, suggesting that they're overworked and ineffectual. On a number of ocassions, Saenz says, he has called the police to report a crime and failed to recieve any response at all. He also discusses the plight of illegal immigrants in his neighborhood, who have been the victims of a number of crimes but are too scared by their immigration status to report crimes to the police. Saenz also describes a neighborhood street festival he recently attended.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Sandine, Robert, 2004 October 26; computer file (WAV)